<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition to the towne of Callays</title>
            <author>R. P., fl. 1557.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1557</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08790)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition to the towne of Callays</title>
                  <author>R. P., fl. 1557.</author>
                  <author>Pownall, Robert, 1520-1571, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>P.A. de Zuttere?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1557]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: R.P., i.e. Robert Pownall?.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: The 12. of April. 1557.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="admonition">
            <pb facs="tcp:20783:1"/>
            <head>¶ AN ADMONITION TO the Towne of Callays.</head>
            <p>VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce how many wayes God hath ſought,<note place="margin">Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goſpel, and Callays fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loueth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.</note> to induce the to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (O Callays, thow towne of myne educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) &amp; on the other ſyde thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; hypocritical diſſimulation in folowinge the footſteppes of thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but with teares lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thyne emyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.</note> as the Prophet Ieremie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled the ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Cyte Ieruſalem.<note place="margin">God hath fought alme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants to call Callays to repentance.</note> For what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hath god done in tymes paſte to other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntries &amp; townes to cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, that he hath nor performed the lyke vnto the, &amp; to thy murmuringe mother, with a great deale more?<note place="margin">Mat. II.</note> Hath he not (as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth) piped vnto the pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, &amp; yet thow haſte not reioyced?<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> Hath he not alſo played vnto the morninge notes, &amp; yet thow haſt not lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted? O what a melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious harmonie was the ſwere ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpel in thine eares, coupled with the ſice re miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; that vnder the autorite of a moſte ℣tuouſe &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t kynge?<note place="margin">Hon Callais hath reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the prechige of the goſpel.</note> But how dideſte thow reioice thereat? For ſothe in the libertie of the fleſh e &amp; nor in the fredome of the ſpirite. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of that ſpiritual melodie, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioiced in his carnalite: the couitou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, in his couitouſnes: the Extorſioner, in his
<pb facs="tcp:20783:2"/>extorſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">The vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed make the goſpel a cloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke for theire vvichednes</note> the a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bitious, in his a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, in his dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenes: the Prowd, in his Pryde: the Adulterer, in his Adulterie, in maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the ſame a cloke for their impietie. Where as thei ſhoulde haue reioiced in a ſpiritual ioye laudi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the lorde that ſo louingly in the middes of darcknes &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie had viſited the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the light of his goſpel. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as God ſaue that this his benignite did no thinge moue thy mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, nor yet the, to reioice in the praiſe of his name,<note place="margin">God for in: gratitude ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth a vvaie his goſpel &amp; ſendeth pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtry.</note> &amp; in the amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy life. Then thought he it highe time to take from you the pipe of mirth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to ſende the morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſonge of ſorrowe &amp; lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For in ſtede of his goſpel he hath ſent you papiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: in ſtede of his holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus maſſe,<note place="margin">For a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an Kïge, god giueth an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Quene. 3. Reg. 18.</note> &amp; vnſa℣y ſacrefice of the bred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god: &amp; in ſtede of a moſte chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kinge, a moſte wicked &amp; idolatrous Quene. A very Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zabel, that is, a frinde to Baal &amp; his priſtes, &amp; an vtter enemie to god &amp; his people. Yea a nother Athalia, that is, an vtter diſtroier of hir owne kinerede,<note place="margin">4. reg. 11.</note> kyngdome &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, a hater of hir owne ſubiectes, a lo℣ of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, &amp; an vnnatural ſtepdame both vnto the &amp; to thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. This is the morninge ſonge that the lorde now ſingeth vnto the, O thow vnkinde Callais. But how doeſt thou morne there at? Forſoth eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as before thou dideſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice. For as before thou dideſt conuarte thy ioye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſpiritual into a carnal reioicinge, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:20783:2"/>ſo now where as thow ſhouldeſt mourne in ſprite, in bewailinge thy ſinnes, ingratitude &amp; infidelite, in repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinge &amp; tourni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto the lorde, who ſeketh al meanes to reclaime the. Thow mourneſt in the fleſh with the Gergeſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes rather for the loſſe of thy hogges,<note place="margin">Mat. 8. Mar. 5. Luc.
8.</note> thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arthly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modites, which Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts hath, &amp; his like to take a waie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the departure of Chriſt, his worde &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.<note place="margin">Callais mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for fere of temporall plages &amp; not for hir ſines as did kinge Achab for the death of Naboth, Luc. 19. Eſa. 5.</note> Thow mourneſt rather for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral plages which <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly thow feleſt, &amp; gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ater forſceſt to folowe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any deſire thou haſt of the kingdome of god, &amp; the floriſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge proſperite of the ſame, which now is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie for thine ingratitude, &amp; for not knowin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the time of thy viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therefor moſte iuſtly hath the lorde broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe the hedge of the Engliſhe churche and made it a praie to the Romiſhe bore, &amp; his ſweiniſhe pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtical pigges, which now vnmercifully wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp the rootes &amp; bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches thereof, in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it with the ſtinki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of diſſaiuable doctrine, &amp; in ſtede of ſwete ſmelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge flowers doeth pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te therein the odiouſe wedes of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie &amp; hypocriſie. The which ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vp at this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that or it be lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, it wilbe thorow ripe for the ſickle of the lordes indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.</note> For the tares of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe &amp;. yeres ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the &amp; thi mother,<note place="margin">Mat.
13.</note> hath brought forth more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of increſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did the good ſeade of the goſpel in 7. yeres before. O la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable alteration. Who euer woulde <pb facs="tcp:20783:3"/>haue ſuppoſed (O Callais) that thow bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo perfitly pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful knowlege of the ℣itie,<note place="margin">Callais in ſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of grapes bringeth forth thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Math. 21. Eſa. 5.</note> &amp; ſo ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiblie hedged about with the ſin cere vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge of the goſpel, as a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vine to ylde ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of good frute, that thow wouldeſt haue brought forth ſuch thornes &amp; breers as appereth in the at this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Who e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer woulde haue thought that Callays co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſo many erneſte goſpellers in outward ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">The doinges of idolaters &amp; hypocri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> that there ſhould haue bi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſene in it, ſuch gaddi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the maſſe, ſuch mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in the pryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes eare, ſuch gapinge after a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge god, ſuch gaddi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge a proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinge of papiſtrie ſuch diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Idolatrie, ſuch regeſtringe of names in the booke of the Beaſte to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cinge of Chriſt, as is &amp; hath byne v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the of late, to the great diſhonour of god, the greuous ſorrowe of thy frindes, &amp; to the no litel reioiſinge of thyne enimies. But it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with equite that ſuch as haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to walke in the ſhini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge light of the goſpel, that thei do ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble &amp; fal into the palpable dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes of errour &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie. For how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be choſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt forſaketh, Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than fourth uvith poceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth. 1. Pet. 5. Mat.
12.</note> but that if the light do lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs, darknes muſt nedes ouerwhelme vs: &amp; if verite ons forſake vs, errour muſt nedes poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſe vs: that is, if Chriſt do reli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhe vs, then muſt Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nedes ceaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For he is that toring lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſeketh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to deuoure. Who, if he ons finde the houſe of our hartes cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſwept &amp; e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pty of godlines, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> retourneth <pb facs="tcp:20783:3"/>he with 7. deuels worſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe, &amp; ſo ſhal oure e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de be worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, the which thinge is al redy ℣ified in a great manie,<note place="margin">1. Pet.
4.</note> who beinge ons cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, do with the ſowe, wallawe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes in the ſtinkinge puddell of papiſtrie againe.</p>
            <p>Wherefor (my derely beloued) I beſeche the in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt (whoſe wealth I wyſhe for as myne awne) that thow do not reſſayue the grace of god in vaine, neither yet be aſhamed of his goſpel, where of in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie he hath made the a partaker, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which thow ſemeſte now to ſlyde a ſide by diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by plainge cole vnder ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delſtick (as the prouerbe goeth) by ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ninge with the hare &amp; holdige with the hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de,<note place="margin">The great diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Callais,</note> by goinge vnto god in thine harte &amp; vnto the deuel in thy body, by ſainge one thinge with thy mouthe &amp; thi kinge the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary with thy mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, much like vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Iſraelites in the tyme of Ieſabels raigne, who couitinge to halt o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both ſydes, with their hartes to ſerue God,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 18.</note> and with their bodis to ſerue Baal, accordinge to the Quenes proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge. They ſtraied from the narowe path of godes ſauour, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the brode waie of his deſple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſure,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> prouokinge him thereby to plage the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de with ſterilite &amp; barrynes ſo that he kepte raine &amp; dewe from the earth for ſpace of in.<note place="margin">3. reg. 17.</note> yeres and vi. mounthes.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare that ſtorie with thy tyme, &amp; ſtate of thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; thow ſhalt finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>agreable <pb facs="tcp:20783:4"/>in no thinge but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in this, that god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des plages are not yet ſo fully performed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the &amp; hir, as fel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but do now firſte of al begine to appere &amp; moſt certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wil followe, al though not in the ſame forme, yet to the like e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, if ſhe &amp; thow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tineue &amp; perſeuere in the like iniquite as you haue begone.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betvvix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Iſrael and Englande. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. reg. 18. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. Reg. 21.</note> For as in the time of Iezabels raigne the prophetes of the lorde were ſlaine in Iſrael, ſo are thei now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſte Naboth loſte hir vini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde by oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo doeth many rightous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de theire la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; poceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The people of god the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iſrael were forced to flee into ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. Reg. 19</note> ſo are thei now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Other were impriſoned &amp; moſt cruelly intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, ſo are they now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. Reg. 18.</note> Other ſome were faine to crepe into holes &amp; caues, ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſte to piller, liuinge in moſte painful pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie, glad to haue bread &amp; water, how many in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at this preſent are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to do the like, experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce teaceth in al partes of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. The Rulers, the Maieſtrates &amp; multitude diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled both with God &amp; the Quene, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do thei now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The lorde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſarued ſo me of the nobilite in Iſrael, as Obadia &amp; other, who ſhowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes ℣y fauorable vnto his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſo hath god likewiſe reſerued ſome of the nobilite of thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (altho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ught thei be but few in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) as wildes to preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyranny of Antichriſt in his blouddy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers (as thow Callais ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly <pb facs="tcp:20783:4"/>witnes the ſame). No thinge doubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge but that thei ſhal finde fauoure with Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia in the ſight of Elias &amp; Iehu,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 18.4. Reg. 9.10.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſhal ſtire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to ouerthrowe the Auters of Baal, and to diſtroie his idolatrous Preſtes, with theire Princeſſe-Iezabel.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As Iſrael &amp; England a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth in ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſo are thei like to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gree in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</note>This farre agreeth Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with Iſrael, and as thei agree i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grauite of ſinnes, ſo (I fere me) thei are like to agree in grauite of poniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For the lorde is the ſame aeternal, immutable God, that he was then, fauorable in mercie vnto the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; iuſte in iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked.</p>
            <p>The plages af Iſrael in the daies of Iezabell were theſe, derth, famine,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 17 18.20.22.</note> and mortalite of man and beaſte, warre, battail, and inuaſion of the enimie, to the great ſpoyl of the lande, and ſlaughter of the people, the kynge ſlaine,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 10.</note> the Quene diſtroied, and al their poſterite conſumed from the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Praier very nedefull for England.</note>This was the Viale of the Lordes indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thoſe daies powred forth vpon Iſrael for the ſinnes of the ſame. Let vs praye that the like or rather greater do not happen vnto Englande, whoſe ſinnes waied in the ballance of Goddes iuſtice, are no doubt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a great deale heuier.</p>
            <p>And thow (Callays) let the ſtate of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria in thoſe dayes be an admonition to moue the to repentance:<note place="margin">4. Reg. 6 Let Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a be a vuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais.</note> which for the ſinnes <pb facs="tcp:20783:5"/>before expreſſed, was not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly beſegede with the power of a moſt puiſant prince, but alſo ſo extremely oppreſſed with famine, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple therein were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, to eate theire owne dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, &amp; the filthe &amp; dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge af theire beaſtes &amp; byrdes: yea, the mothers were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to eate their owne childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch was the wooful wrath of god vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſinful diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; declininge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god to Idolatrie, as wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth the holy ſcriptures.<note place="margin">4. Reg.
6</note> Let that exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple (I ſaie) O Callays moue the to throw downe &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble thy ſelfe vndre the mighty ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of god in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſinge thy ſinnes, &amp; bewailige thy wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knes, that ſo ſone haſte bin o℣blowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo litel a blaſte of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Callais is go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne back fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goſpell vnto papiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> That ſo ſone haſte go ne backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truthe &amp; pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, vnto that polluted puddel of papiſtry by diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where as thy duety had bin be ſore many other (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering thine ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelick profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vniuerſally knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to haue ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſtedfaſte in the truthe, hauiuge for thy manifeſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therein, the moſte certai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne worde of god, the teſtimonie of thine ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the exäple of a gret no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t marters, &amp; the continual admonition of many godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, now flede into ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to ſaue theire lifes for a praie vntil the determinate ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, &amp; in the meane ceaſon to be profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you at home.</p>
            <p>Wherfor as thine vnfained frinde &amp; lo℣
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a one as for thy preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coulde be <pb facs="tcp:20783:5"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to taſte much miſerie) do erneſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horte the to fle vnto repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance,<note place="margin">The oneli re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medi to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Calais from diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion, is repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance.</note> the onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallible remedie, able not onely to reſtore thy health, but alſo to preſerue the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtruction wich is emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ouer thy beade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nota.</note>For what kingdome or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, Citie or tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was there e℣ that beinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the like ſicknes of ſinne,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.8.19. 4. reg. 17. Dan. 5. Vvith Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Danes. Brito<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and nou vvith Spaniardes.</note> did not pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhe therein, if this reſaiued remedie did not <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame. For wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this remedie, was not the firſte worlde drowned? Samaria diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Babelo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one night ſubuerted? And thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thriſe with ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers infected, &amp; now the fourth time like to be deſolated? Yf this remedie of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do not ſpedely <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it? On the other ſide where as this reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath bin in time reſaiued, the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger bein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ne℣ ſo great, yet hath it al waies deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of leruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Beru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia, Niniue &amp; many other do euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare, which onely by this meanes, as teſtifieth the ſcriptures, remoued the plages <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſently purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O that thow hadeſte the like grace to fle vnto this remedie in this thine ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prochinge peril: which although thow (blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the loue of thy ſelfe, carnal ſecurite,<note place="margin">Other <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies ſeeth not.</note> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in thine owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght) doeſt not now preſaiue, yet thy fri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, who with a more vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eye watche ouer thy wealth do eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly behold ſpedely to approche. Wherefor (I ſaie) in time riſe vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſinne. Ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:20783:6"/>thine idolatrie. Throwe awaie the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tel of thine hypocriſie. Waſhe thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, &amp; be contented rather to ſuffer afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſainctes of god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with eaſe to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioye the pleaſure of ſinne for a ceaſon, the ende where of wilbe thy vtter ſubuerſion. For true<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thow that haſte refuſed to drike of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cuppe of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his holions, thou ſhalt moſt certainely taſte of the dregges of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the wicked: where of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is like ſhortly to be a partaker. For there is no token that is the foregoer of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">All tokens vvhich are the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led in engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> but it is apparant in hir. For if the ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of godes pure religion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crectin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vp of idolatrie &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the raginge raigne of traiterous tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the dayly decaye of the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; honorable, the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie of the clargie,<note place="margin">Eſa. 3.</note> the diſſembling impietie of the laiety, the abonda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhedinge of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloude, the cruel impriſoninge, baniſhinge &amp; perſecutinge of the ſeruantes of God. If the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſignes (I ſaie) haue al waies bin the forgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of rewyne &amp; diſtruction, as the ſtories of the holy ſcriptures doeth euidently witneſſe, then let not thine vnſaightful mother thinke to eſcape the ſame, in whom at this preſent al theſe tokens are euident. And eſpecially the vniuerſal ſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge of the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud of the conſtant witneſſes of Ieſus Chriſt now flowinge through out euery Shire, Cyty and <pb facs="tcp:20783:6"/>Towne cryinge for ſpedy vengance: The which with out al doubt is cominge, euen as it were with in a kenninge.<note place="margin">vvhen Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is plaged let not Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais thine to eſcape free.</note> And doeſt thow thincke (O Callais) thow that arte the doughter of ſo wycked a mother (if thow be founde partaker of hir impiety, that thow ſhalte not taſte of hir plages? Yeas truely: And that paraduenture with the fyrſte.</p>
            <p>For commonly when as God purpoſeth to ponyſhe the parent, he beginneth with the chylde. And therefor thy lott ys ſo much the nerer, for that thow doeſt not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly lye in the waye of the enemye as a butte againſt his arrowe,<note place="margin">Callais is co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uited of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</note> but alſo forthy ſtrenght, beawty and commodite thow art deſyred of many. And that thinge (as ſayeth the prouerbe) with much a do is preſerued, that is of diuers couited and deſyred,<note place="margin">Callais is in the cuſtody of a vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> eſpeciallye when as the cuſtodie thereof is in the handes of a woman, who with great difficultye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſtrayne any Iewel that ſhe hath from him, whom ſhe loueth, he crauinge the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nota. Vvhy the hinge loueth the Quene.</note>And doeſt thow thynck that he wyll not craue, who loueth hir onely for hyr trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and Iewels, and not for hir perſon?</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſeſte show that he wyll not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the (the nexte Iewel vnto the beſte,<note place="margin">Callais the nexte ieuell vnto the beſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te.</note> and lyinge ſo much for his commodyte) that hath all redy attempted to haue all togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Yeas be thow ſure of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20783:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The braggi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge boſte of the Spaniar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note>The Spaniardes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boſte &amp; make their auaſite that if their kinge had the, he would both bry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>del Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; rule Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at his pleaſure. And therefor he ſeketh but oportunite, to optaine, that which his harte ſo much deſireth.
<note place="margin">The french Kinge vvat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth but for oportunite to recouer Callais.</note>On the other ſide the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which his anceſters of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge time haue loſte. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for that pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe was there euer better occaſion miniſtred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent? For thy mother the ſtaffe of thy defence,<note place="margin">England at this preſent ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t able to helpe callais</note> is now ſo debilitated &amp; weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as wel in worthy Captaines &amp; valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Sol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diours, as in mony, monitions &amp; victail, that ſhe is ſcant able to defende, &amp; releue hir ſelfe: much les then to ſuccor the in thy neceſſite. Thus art chow inuironed with enimies on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſyde,<note place="margin">Callais van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting frendes, is inuironed vvith eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> without hauinge any aſſured frinde to leane vnto. Wherefor I admoniſhe the to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider thy <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent ſtate, before it be to late, &amp; in to what eminent danger thy ſinne hath brought the. But whether now wilt thow turne the for they preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">pſal. 137. The ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght of Callais is to vveahe for hir defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, if the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de do not ꝓ teete theſa. me.</note> Vnto thine ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght? Alas in veine. For in vaine doeth the watchma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> watch the Cyte, if the lorde do not kepe the ſame. And how ſhal he kepe the, thow that haſt made no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to forſake him the wholſome water of life, in digginge vp againe the filthy Ceſtoms of papiſtrie &amp; Idolatrie. wilt thow turne the for helpe vnto thy worthy Gouernour &amp; prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailourst In vaine alſo.<note place="margin">callais is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to loſe hir frindes.</note> For they ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:20783:7"/>the. Wilt thow require aide of ſome of the no bilite that ſeme to fauour the. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſhal betraie the. For how ſhould they loue the, that paſſe not of thy mother, but ſeke al poſſible meanes to alie nate hir fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enhe ritors vnto forriners &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally wilt thou ſeke for ſuccour of thy ancient Soldiours &amp; worthy warriours, of thy louin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons &amp; wealthy marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? That is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in vaine. For with what hartes ſhal thei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſende the (theire towne, the ſtaffe of theyre earthly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modites) that haue ſhowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes ſo faint harted in ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge to the ℣ire of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, the ſhoranker of their aeternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As eaſely wil their ſuffer them ſelfes to be thretened &amp; pſuaded to reſigne the o℣, as they haue al redy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaded without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, to relinquiſhe the pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, &amp; the fredome of the goſpel, to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the bonde ſlaues of Antichriſte the Pope. For truely ſuch as haue ſhowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes fait harted in the one, cannot be valiant in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: excepte ſuch as haue ſetled their ſouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aigne felicite on earthly thinges, whoſe atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly the lorde doeth not proſper. For ſuch as for the ſafegard of theire lifes do denie him, &amp; yet for the preſeruation of temporal thinges do haſſarde the ſame, thei do thereby plainely declare; how litel thei regarde heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; how much thei are addicte vnto the earth. Who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly (ſuch is the iuſte iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <pb facs="tcp:20783:8"/>God) in ſekinge to ſaue their goodes, do loſe theyre liffes, in that they haue no thynge eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emed the lyffe of the Soule in reſpecte of the earthly pleaſures here. But whether now (O Callays) wylt thow turne the in this thy ne extreme neceſſite? Euen vnto the Lorde God thyne onely ſoueraigne remedie: Who onely in ryme of nede is able to preſerue and delyuer the: and now onely able, but alſo moſte wyllynge, ſo thow turne the vnto him. For he hath promiſed by his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that if we turne vnto him,<note place="margin">Zach. 1. ler. 3. Ioel. 2. Hou Callais ought to tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto the Lorde, Eſa. 1.</note> he wil turne vnto vs, to ſhowe mercye vpon vs. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refor O thow backſlydinge Towne turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde thy God with al thy harte, from thy wicked waies, forſake thy ſinnes, caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie thyne abhominations, and then ſhalt thow lyue, and the wrath of God ſhalbe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into mercye. Turne vnto the lorde thy God (I ſaie) in repentance,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> in fayght, in hattred of thy ſinnes, in confeſſinge of thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne offences, and in the amendment of thy lyffe. Turne vnto the Lorde thy God with the Cytes of Niniue and Betulia,<note place="margin">Ionas. 3. Iudith. 8.</note> and then wil the Lorde beholde the with mercie, and couer the vnder the whynges of his defence.</p>
            <p>He wilbe thy Buckler, thy ſpere and ſhilde. He wil be thy fortreſſe, thy wal and bulwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Al thyne enimies ſhall not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the. They may beſege the, they <pb facs="tcp:20783:8"/>may ſubtelly conſpire to betraye the, but all in vaine.<note place="margin">pſal.
31.91.</note> For the Lorde wil be thy watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Yea, he himſelfe wil ringe the Alarom, Sound the trompet, Stryke vp the drome, &amp; auance thy Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dart agaynſt thyne aduerſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, in mouinge thyne harte into thyne owne defence, and aſſiſte the in the ſame, as a thinge lawfull both by the lawes of God,<note place="margin">Nota</note> the lawes of the Lande, and inſtincte of nature. For thow art not ſo farre ſworne to obaie, as by obedience to ſhowe thy ſelfe a Traytreſſe to thyne owne country:<note place="margin">hovu farre Callais is ſubiecte to the Quene.</note> Neyther art thow ſo ſubiect to ths Quene, as for hir ſake, to with drawe for euer thy ſubiection from the crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of Englande, and the ryghtful enhaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the ſame. Wherefore take hede: and make the Lorde of hoſtes be tymes thy frynde, and then thow nedeſte not to paſſe who is thyne enemye.<note place="margin">god vvil be vvraie the attemptes of traitors.</note> For he wyl bewraye the diſſemblinge deuyces of thy fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned fryndes (but ſecret enemies) as he did the trayterouſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Achitophel, againſt his ſeruant Dauid.<note place="margin">2 Reg. 17</note>
            </p>
            <p>For it is he that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the deuyces of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly into theyr owne deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wherefore gett the be tymes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his defence, and thow ſhalt not nede to fere the power of al thy aduerſaryes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20783:9"/>
            <p>But if thow diſpice this frindly admonition,<note place="margin">Callais is ſie he, but ſhe fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth it not.</note> perſuadinge thy ſelfe that thow art in a better caſe, then in dede thow art, as the moſt parte of wordly perſons do, euen in the extremite of death perſuade vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfeslo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge life: Thow ſhalt ſurely periſhe in thy ſinnes. Beleue not thoſe flattringe Phariſes that crie out in euery pulpet,<note place="margin">The plages of England vuil come o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer to Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais as did the ſvveti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiones,</note> peace, peace, plenty, plentye, when as famine &amp; diſtruction is at hande. Which now beginneth to appere in thy mother Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; wil ſhortly approche vnto the, al thoughe thou canneſte not foreſee the meanes, how, nor the time, whan. For of this be thow ſure that God doeth neuer leaue ſuch impiete. as is in the, longe u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poniſhed. The waie to auoide it I haue ſhewed the, if now through thy negligence thow periſhe,<note place="margin">If callais nou periſhe, it is not for vant of vvarni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge</note> thy blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyne owne head. For I am free from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Saie not but that thow art warned.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Exile
<date>the .12. of April. 1557.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Wicked people bringeth a Citie into decaie: but wyſſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet it vp againe.</p>
                  <bibl>Prouerb. 29.</bibl> 
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:20783:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
